Table, sorry.
Brick.
Hemp brick.
Make a house.
Yeah.
Make a boat.
It'll float.
You can build lots with that. Yeah.
Is it water-repellent? Like, it doesn't absorb water, no?
No.
It looks like it would, doesn't it?
Like it-
No, but it's, well, it does absorb some water, but it filters
out.
So it's hydrophobic.
When you line it with plaster as well, then you've got a
seal, haven't you? But it's sealed.
Right.
It'll meet the building code for weather-tight and water-tight
and that sort of thing.
Should I pass this down?
Please.
I feel like it,
the microphones will pick up very distant.
There you go.
Thanks, Margaret.
They're not edibles. Morning, Richard.
Really nice to see you back.
What we were really after is an update on,
since we've had you in last,
how things have changed or not changed, and-
Yes
... what
we may be able to do to assist the industry.
We've
certainly
seen some changes that the Ministry of Regulation announced actually
not long after you presented to us last time.
And there was some work going on between
NPI and the Ministry of Health to make sure that
some of the barriers that you raised were not going to be a barrier in the
future. So, I'll leave it with you.
Well, I'm sure we're going to have an interesting conversation.
Yeah.
So thank you for the opportunity. I've just prepared to
go along with the documents that we shared,
just a brief statement so I can cover all the points.
It'll only take about five or six minutes to read.
So I'll just whip through that first-
Okay
... and then we can have some questions and I'll provide the
answers. So Chair, members of the committee, thank you for the opportunity to
appear before you today.
I'm speaking on behalf of the New Zealand Hemp Industries Association.
Firstly, I'd like to acknowledge the committee's continued interest in industrial
hemp.
We appreciate your engagement over the past two years and the opportunity to
continue the discussions following the recent regulatory reform.
The association also appreciates the work undertaken by the Ministry of Regulation.
The review represented the first significant reform of industrial hemp regulations
in 20 years. We publicly, excuse me, we publicly
welcome those changes. Today, I'd like to briefly discuss three things,
what has been achieved, what opportunities remain, and where government and
industry can work together over the next two years.
Industrial hemp is no longer a simple agricultural crop.
Around the world, it is becoming an important raw material for food, fiber,
construction materials, as you can see with the hemp block, and
internet, and textiles, bio composites, and the emerging
bioeconomy. New Zealand has genuine competitive
advantages. We already have world-class farming systems,
excellent traceability, a strong research sector, and an
international reputation for producing high-quality natural products.
The international market is growing rapidly.
Our opportunity is not simply to grow, it is to build high-value
processing industries and export both products and the
technologies developed here in New Zealand.
This is where the long-term economic value lies.
The recent reforms removed one of the industry's biggest frustrations.
Replacing the Ministry of Health license with a notification process has
significantly reduced compliant costs for growers
and those processing seed.
That was a practical and sensible decision, and increasing the
THC to 1% has given us access to more genetics.
Removing licenses has
also attracted considerable international attention because New Zealand has
demonstrated that industrial hemp can be regulated using a proportionate
risk-based approach. For that, the industry is genuinely
grateful.
However, these reforms primarily benefit cultivation, the growers, and the
seed processors. They did not substantially improve opportunities for full plant
utilization or manufacturing innovative products.
The largest barrier today sits further along the value chain.
Industrial hemp remains regulated under the Misuse of Drugs Act.
Oh.
Despite the United Nations Single Convention specifically excluding
low-THC industrial hemp grown for industrial and horticultural
purposes.
While growers can now produce the crop more easily, much of the plant cannot be
used commercially except through the situation medicinal
cannabis pathways.
That means that leaves and flowers and roots remain unavailable for health and
wellness products.
The current prohibition on hemp ingredients for production in companion animals
also limits commercial opportunities and reduces full plant
utilization.
These restrictions make investment more difficult.
Businesses are reluctant to invest in processing infrastructure where large
portions of the crop have no commercial pathway.
CBD is now the central issue. From an industry perspective, THC
is no longer the primary regulatory challenge, although getting out of
MODA remains the NZHIA's number one objective.
Modern industrial hemp contains extremely low levels of THC and routinely tests
well below regulatory thresholds.
The remaining challenge is CBD.
Because naturally occurring CBD is regulated as a prescription
medicine under the Medicines Act, industrial hemp biomass can generally
only enter the medicinal cannabis supply pathway.
Otherwise, we are forced to treat it as contaminant in our industrial hemp crops.
This effectively prevents development of a broader health and wellness
industry based on industrial hemp.
Addressing this issue would unlock significant innovation while maintaining
appropriate safeguards around therapeutic products.
Growing hemp is only the first step.
The real economic opportunity lies in processing, manufacturing, and developing
new products. That requires investment, it requires infrastructure, it
requires research, and it requires confidence that regulations
will continue evolving in a practical and evidence-based manner.
The association is encouraged by the strong relationships we have developed with
research organizations, universities, and innovation centers across New Zealand.
The capability exists. What is needed now is a regulatory environment that
allows investment to follow.
Looking ahead, the Ministry for Regulation has committed to reviewing these
regulations again in two years. That provides an excellent opportunity.
Between now and then, we can gather evidence, support responsible industry
growth,
and identify when further improvements can safely be made.
The NZHA is already contributing through education, industry guidance, and the
New Zealand
Hemp Industries Association Seed Product, helping new growers
adopt best practices while maintaining industry integrity.
Our requests, we respectfully ask the committee to continue
supporting practical and evidence-based reform.
In particular, we encourage government to continue progressing, getting
industrial hemp out of the Misuse of Drugs Act,
finally
allowing us to realize the full plant utilization and releasing us from the
burdens and regulations. Review the treatment of naturally
occurring CBD and low-THC industrial hemp that's leading to that health and
wellness industry. Support development of a health products framework.
Revisit the restrictions of hemp for companion and production animals
using evidence-based risk assessment.
Support research, standards, and processing capability that will allow New Zealand
to compete internationally and encourage investment into commercially viable
hemp businesses and regional processing infrastructure.
These are practical steps that will help industry grow responsibly while creating
regional jobs, supporting innovation, and contributing to New Zealand's emerging
bio-economy.
The 2026 reforms were an important milestone, and the industry
sincerely thanks the government and officials for the progress that has been made,
but they are only the beginning. We now have an opportunity to build a modern
industrial hemp industry that delivers economic, environmental, and regional
development benefits for New Zealand.
Our association looks forward to continuing to work constructively with government
and with this committee ahead of the next review.
Thank you,
and over to questions.
Thanks, Richard. We'll go straight to Mark Cameron, News.
Good morning, Richard, and thank you so much for
your time. We're very grateful for your time.
I'm interested to know,
obviously you'll have a pipeline of opportunity
costs and opportunities gained.
Where do you see yourself in five years' time?
We've
certainly seen this committee very, very active in trying to create an
environment that would give the hemp industry all the opportunities it
deserves.
But you surely to goodness have a pipeline of aspiration, and what does that look
like?
Well, if we're looking for a five-year horizon, then
one of the milestones will be the review of the Ministry for Regulation's-
Yeah
...
changes that they made this year. So that's in two years' time.
So we'll be working towards that to provide the information and evidence to
support the removal of low-THC industrial hemp out of the
Misuse of Drugs Act, because we're just another agricultural,
arable, or horticultural crop.
Mm.
And that would really free us up. So the regulations as they
stand did make a difference for the grower.
They no longer need a license. They can just notify the police and Ministry of
Primary Industries.
So that's the supply chain. But that's not really where the bottleneck sits.
It's the value chain is where we need to be developing innovative
products. So in five years' time, I'd like to see pet foods
available. Well, within one or two years, I would like to see pet foods available.
I'd like to see some trials done in the very short term on production
animals, because we only have a very small amount of these co-products
coming out of the hemp seed industry that could be used rather than being put into
a 40-foot container and shipped overseas-
Mm
... or disposed in a landfill. So, full plant
utilization means that we need the economics of all those parts
of the plant to work in our favor, and we need access to those markets.
So working through with MPI, ACVM on the
issue of production animals, which
was ruled out of scope from the Ministry
of Regulation's
deliberations, so they couldn't do anything with that particular issue.
Now, that was one of the biggest issues facing the industry.
So great, the growers are moving forward, but without those markets, it's very
burdensome still in the sense that we don't have access to the economics that we
need. So the animal food issue would be a great
one to overcome in the next five years.
And this treatment of CBD as a prescription medicine under the Medicines Act
complicates things unnecessary for industrial hemp.
The medicinal cannabis scheme has its own way of doing things.
They have their own regulatory
involvement with the Ministry of Health.
We are now no longer really involved with the Ministry of Health unless we want to
import or export because of that low level of THC.
But going back to the CBD, it's a massive problem because it's
naturally occurring in our plant, as are a number of other cannabinoids that all
have commercial interest, along with terpenes and flavonoids.
So
not being able to make products from the leaf and the
flower and the roots is a massive problem.
So our arable industry for food and fiber, that's going to continue to go
ahead, as we've discussed, without the need for a license.
That's removed again, a burdensome
regulation that cost money for compliance.
So that's gone. But
when we look at the horticultural industry, which is this part where we're looking
at these health and wellness products, it's really problematic because
there's global demand for them. There's Demand in New Zealand for them.
But we can't access that market because of the treatment of the Medicines
Act
making CBD a prescription medicine.
Now, at certain high doses, it probably is a therapeutic and a medicine.
But when it's naturally occurring in the plant, we can't take it out,
but it's restricting us. So, there's a room,
in the association's opinion, for the Ministry of Health
to look at the Medicines Act and look at the Medicinal Cannabis scheme and say,
"Except for industrial hemp," something like that.
But again, removing us as a prohibitive plant from the Misuse of Drugs Act would
also aid that as well, because we're not a drug, we're an arable and cultural crop.
So in five years' time, you could open up sort of all sorts of opportunities,
and significant money would be involved because you're leading to
export-led
market development. And that's where our aspirational
goals and
the things like Dr. Nick Marsh's
investment strategies in 2020. When the Ministry for
regulation came in and spoke to you, it was like, "Oh, the industry's worth about a
million." Well, industry thinks it's worth about 9 or 10 million currently,
but that could really expand in the near future if we had access to these
markets. The markets that will continue to grow, given
our current regulatory settings, would be in the fiber and the
food side. But with this document in 2020,
the biggest number in there for export potential was in that health and
wellness products, because these are small items, highly valuable,
making use of our provenance story,
enhancing New Zealand with quality export products
backed by the New Zealand farming systems, which are world-class, and introducing
traceability and those sort of things in there.
So those would be the things in five years' time I would like to see those markets
open up. And with regard to the fiber,
it would be great to see the
hempcrete block and
hempcrete building materials and other building materials, the
insulation materials, all coming from those parts of the fiber of
the stem of the plant. And from a food point of view, gaining more
traction,
getting them recognized in the mainstream, working on
economies of scale. So this is where the opportunity to work with
genetics, one way to increase a farmer's return is increase the
yield that they could get. So a bit of the breeding going on there for the seed
yield and things like that. But also looking at what makes New Zealand hemp
special.
Given our growing environment, given our light and our
volcanic soils and things, is there ways that we can differentiate ourselves in the
market globally? I see the hemp seed oil particularly
as that's a global commodity, and that could get up there with the wine
industry, where we work together and keep the standards high for
consumers overseas and overseas markets. And these overseas markets are developing.
This industry is one of probably the few industries currently that
are growing at double-digit compound annual growth rates.
So that's been the story for the last 10 to 15 years.
So if that continues, which it will, then there's real economic
opportunities out there for us. So in five years' time, I'd like to see it, yeah,
getting close to the aspirations of moving it way
beyond the $30 million mentioned in another report,
and growing from there.
Thank you, Richard. Brilliant.
Barbara, you had a question.
Yeah. It's kind of frustrating because that piece in the middle is missing.
One of the things that
over the years, the Natural Health Products Bill
has dragged on and on and on to the point where,
say a few months ago, could have been longer, it was actually withdrawn in
terms of being able to make it useful again.
And so it seems to be from a health perspective, they
talk about a billion-dollar industry that's got caught up with New Zealand
regulations that sits under Health.
What association have you had with any other industries
around the natural health products?
I think there seems to be an opportunity here
to work together to get that
part of it right, because it seems silly to me that we can grow it-
And not use it
... we can't make something out of it.
And I know there's lots of other people in that natural health product space that
have that same issue. So are you
connected with them in any way?
Yes, we work with the Natural Health Products Association.
Yeah.
And
they're following it with interest.
And we're happy to,
again, like hemp is part of the bioeconomy from a fiber point of view and a food
point of view, same with the natural health products.
We're just one of a number of natural health products which would
benefit from having a natural health products framework.
Mm.
And if we can achieve that, then the rising tide lifts all boats.
So,
yes, we would definitely be calling for it, and we'll be supporting their endeavors
as much as we can, and putting forward the economic case of
adding hemp to existing natural health products.
There's a massive industry already exists, and it's a very collegial
industry in the sense that they're making products that are
similar or competitive, but they're all doing it together.
Mm.
And it's a bit of a New Zealand way of doing it because you can go, we
could tap into NZTE, you could go overseas with it, you join others.
And really, you're obviously promoting your product, but by
promoting the sector, it all grows.
And there's some things we can do under the Dietary Supplements Act as well.
But again, it comes back to this treatment of CBD because if that's detected, then
it's a problem.
Yeah. The reason for asking that question, Mr.
Chair, is there's a roadblock there in the health, I think the health,
some conversation, this group and the health committee might be
useful, because farm-
That was going to be my next question, actually, yeah
... yeah, the growers are losing a lot.
So,
how much interaction you had with the Ministry of Health to-
Resolve this, and how supportive do you think they are
of getting this
roadblock cleared?
I think
we've had quite a lot of interactions with the Ministry of Health, of course, about
the Industrial Hemp Regulations 2006 that ultimately were
reformed into 2026.
Mm-hmm.
That's probably taken up lots of the energy for it.
The Ministry of Health were in favor of,
as we were, of removing hemp from needing a license, which was
option four from the Ministry for regulation, which was a bold move.
They no longer require a license. That's international news.
The thing about that is that
they've been quite successful because they don't want to deal with an arable crop
or a horticultural crop.
Mm.
And our farmers don't want to deal with the Ministry of Health amongst everybody
else that they have to deal with. So there's a win there.
But the conversation gets bogged down with our
connection as cannabis to the Misuse of Drugs Act,
THC, as we've described. We're semi out of that because they realize
it's low risk. They're not interested in an arable crop.
So if we look for the horticultural crop, back to your question, Barbara, about
the natural health products, then it becomes problematic
because of the way they've treated CBD and the Medicines
Act. So now we're being knocked on the head with that.
So that's why I say it's one of the major issues facing us.
So with regard to dialogue with them,
we're working on some approaches, and it's just
the people that we've been dealing with in the
Medsafe, and the medicinal cannabis, and industrial hemp sort of
area that looks after the administration, there's not a lot they can
do because they're looking at a piece of legisl- you know, the regulations and
going, "Well, we
can only do what we can do in that." So it becomes a policy
issue, which comes down to political will.
So when we started this process in
2023 with the strategic document, and I did a whole lot of
meetings in '24, came to the Primary Production Select Committee then.
It has cross-party support. Yes, there's still some
stigma around it because some people just hear hemp and jump straight to
cannabis, straight to marijuana, and it's a problem.
But the people that are aware of the construction materials and all these other
materials, and again, if we're focusing on the natural health products,
there's growing market demand for those products.
So it's quite frustrating for the industry not to be able to access
them. To get access to them would require political will.
So you don't see
that sector
having
a lot of opposition from the medical
experts, et cetera,
if at some stage we decide to change the leg
or the regulations around the horticulture
uses. You don't think there will be
an outcry from them?
From the Ministry of Health point of view, again, the reluctance
around a natural health products framework would exist for
our products as well. But that said, though,
at the high doses that an isolate put into a
medicine, and it's a CBD or a THC medicine-
Yeah
... that's right up there. But generally, we can quote
the UN as-
Yeah
... Single Convention is not interested in CBD at all.
WHO and the European community have said that
CBD is non-addictive, it's a
safe product. So at naturally occurring levels in a
plant,
then there shouldn't be too much pushback.
And we're not making medical claims, so we're not wanting to be part of the
therapeutic framework. We just want to have access to the health and
wellness products. And CBD is stopping the consumer
getting involved with not only
limited amounts of CBD and hemp, but it's all these minor cannabinoids, these
terpenes and flavonoids, that also have constructive commercial uses, but
make wonderful products that are of use to people in that
market of that health and wellness market.
Thank you. Rachel.
So there'll be some issues, but we can overcome that.
Yeah.
Yeah. And we touched on it a little bit, but I'm just interested in knowing if you
do regular research into public views, because I think
that you touched on it before about how people hear hemp and often think
something quite different. And so I'm just wondering on that public,
have you been tracking the kind of understanding and views of the public
over the last few years in terms of how they see hemp?
We're a voluntary organization, so we-
So you don't have the resources to do that.
That would be one observation. But over the years, you can see it.
For a period there,
people wouldn't say to me, "Can I smoke my hat?" When I was selling hats at the
market and things like that.
Yeah.
But that's a reaction similar to what with the Brit.
It's a reaction people have.
Yes.
But it reinforces that stigma and-
Yeah
... this is where the work from the Ministry for Regulation really did
help as well because it
gave the credibility to industrial hemp.
And we're not going to turn around and start calling it hemp as
the regulation suggests now, because it's always industrial hemp, and that
perception-
Yeah
... is important for the consumer to understand.
Yeah.
And the reluctance of some people for the food industry, "Am I going to fail a drug
test if I eat hemp seed oil?" No, you're not.
But it was a question. So, we needed more education
there, and that's something that the Ministry of Health's announcement helped
with. But there's other ways that we could do that as well.
It could be in the government procurement.
If you want healthy school lunches, maybe start using hemp seed in your lunches.
If you want green and healthy and sustainable buildings, start thinking about
hempcrete. Help us with those standards to get that information out there.
So there's some really good things we can do.
But the cons-
If I looked at it from a 20-year or 30-year perspective, it's massively
different now. People aren't
as full of reefer madness and anti-marijuana
crossing over to hemp as they are. They can see the difference.
We're not marijuana. We're very low THC, and so
that is helping, and it's gaining traction.
When I talk to hemp now, it's about, oh, hempcrete, or it's about
protruded fiber products and rebar that they're making
out of it for construction. All these sustainable uses in
these heavily intensive
CO2 sort of situations. Those industries that aren't that
sustainable when using fossil fuels, whereas the consumer, I think, is
coming around to realizing that they can grow annually-
Mm
... what we need-
... rather than extracting it as a fossil fuel.
Mm.
And Henry Ford said, "Whatever you can make out of hydrocarbons, you can
make out of carbohydrates." So if they could do that in the 19th century, or the
20th century rather, I'm sure we can do very well now.
Mm.
So it's an opportunity, and that's where New Zealand lies.
Our R&D ecosystem is absolutely engaged.
They just need to have, obviously, industry
support, but government support towards doing some foundational
work would lead to all sorts of commercial opportunities, and especially in the
fiber-
Yes
... into construction materials, composites, plastics.
These lightweight things are really gaining traction.
Graphene, replacing graphene in batteries, that sort of thing.
You can make it all out of hemp, and we've got a really good understanding, and
that ecosystem, as I say, from New Zealand Product Accelerator,
the bioscience,
the new CRIs all coming together, they're all very engaged with it.
And so they're wanting to use that
significant resource of 1,700 odd scientists to really apply it, and
that's New Zealand's gift to the world because if we did embrace it,
we could be using it to make the processing equipment,
the tech, and then you license that overseas because everybody in
the world is trying to scale their industry. And we're successfully doing so.
The Carfields have brought on a decorticator.
There's another two decorticators, one at Hemp Central in Wanaka, and Venture
Taranaki. So that's now stimulating the fiber side.
But to scale into the
realms of competing with fossil fuels as a raw material for industry,
you've got to scale up, and this is a real opportunity for us.
And all that equipment needs to be developed and understood.
We're still using 20th century technology, early 20th century
technology.
Sue.
Fantastic submission. Thank you very much, and really appreciate your passion
for the industry.
Thank you.
So, simply put, the first task is to get it out of the Misuse of Drugs
Act. Is that right? Would that-
That's our number one objective
... make a significant difference in terms of your return on investment and your,
and everything that you-
Future growth, yeah
... and future growth and cost of production.
I imagine it's impeding your cost of production too, the regulatory frameworks,
maybe?
Well, in the sense that it's halting a whole sector.
Yeah.
Holding the growth. And then I was interested in that you were, in your submission,
in fact, it could be said we're now further away than when the
definitions of industrial hemp and hemp products were in place under the
2006 regulations. So it's got worse
before it's got better.
In a sense, yes, because
under the 2006 industrial regulations, the hemp definition of a hemp
product was anything made from hemp, and hemp was--
Sorry, industrial hemp it was called then, which is low THC industrial hemp.
Yeah.
So we could make any product. So I could make a case for
making a natural health product. Then I would have to deal with the end
use legislation the same as I would with food or the building code for fiber and
things. Whereas now they've changed, the Ministry of Health have taken an
opportunity to tighten that definition.
So hemp product is now can't be made from all parts of the plant.
It's only the stem and the seed. So then you're left with the leaf and the roots,
and the flower of the plant, which previously
I could've made a case for being able to be used in a market.
Now we have a new baseline on our not so level playing
field that says, "No, you can't."
You must supply that to a medicinal cannabis company.
Or presumably, we may be able to export it,
and bypass the New Zealand economy to the straight away,
go global from day one. So which is great for the global community, but not
so good for New Zealand. So that's why I referred to that.
It has made it a little bit more difficult.
But it has given us that new baseline, so we know where we stand.
Roots was always a bit,
in the gray area. We argued that the roots are part of the stem, so
they're a stem, and the stems were always a hemp product and there was no
restrictions. But now they've taken the opportunity to tell us, "No,
that's your new..." So we've got this baseline. This is where we're working for.
We know where we stand now in 2026. What can
we do? What can we prove? Evidence we can raise,
arguments that we can put together,
to justify changing it within that two-year review.
So that two-year review is very, very important for the industry because that
brings into light an opportunity to
have this conversation again somewhere, and show where the
world's gone, where these products could've been, because that's the opportunity
cost we're missing.
Right. Final questions, Steve.
Mine's sort of a bit of an observation, whether you want to respond or not, but I
feel like the paradox of
hemp and cannabis more broadly is that its problem is it does too many
things. It's such a super species
that you can make clothes from it- Oh, well- ...
you can make building materials from it, you can eat it, it's medicinal, it does
all the things, and that's actually part of its challenge.
And so it seems that we have to get over the, we have to--
It's kind of ridiculous that we find ourselves in a situation where we can't
utilize it because it does everything.
Mm-hmm.
Yeah. Which is very frustrating. And the hemp industry, what is the hemp
industry? Well, it's part of the food industry, it's part of the building industry,
it's part of the composite industry, health and wellness industry, as we discussed.
So yeah, we've got too many points, not enough penetration.
But that's a-- The industry will drive that, the people passionate in
those areas about food or about composite materials or about graphene
or plastics, textiles. They'll push it for themselves.
Mm.
Mm. So, that's where the investment from our point of view, particularly in fiber,
comes in because that's the primary processing step.
We need that infrastructure to get out the two commodities that then can feed
into those, some of those channels, as can seed.
But in seed's case, we can't use animals, so changing the companion animals,
production animal situation is probably equally as important for
many members as the CBD situation.
So that's the one that we can really work on with you guys at the Primary
Production Select Committee, because having a ban on both production and
companion doesn't make sense because of the perceived trade risk.
That only involves production, so free up companion.
Perceived trade risk. Is there any evidence for that?
Mm.
No. Have they done any work to quantify the problem?
These are really big issues. So those two issues are the big ones-
Okay, right
... CBD and animal foods.
Don't leave the pets and dogs.
Thanks very much,
Richard. I really appreciate you, as Sue said, your passion and your
advocacy for the industry.
Thank you.
That was really useful to get that briefing, give us an
understanding of where we're at and where we need to go. So thank you very much.
Thank you for the opportunity, sir.
I had the final briefing picked right up on those two points because we'll carry on
working on them, but with your support-
Yeah
... political will-
... we can get there.
No.
Thank you so much.
Thank you, guys.
It'd be good to untie one of your hands from behind your back so you can go for it.
Exactly.
I
wonder if that, if that, I was trying to think if the,
not the Hasno, the other one with health-